Guide to the Montauk Club collection BCMS.0045
Brooklyn Collection
Montauk Club collection
1889-2016
Brooklyn Collection
BCMS.0045
6.2 Linear Feet in 10 boxes
Records, photographs, and ephemera from the Montauk Club, a social club in Park Slope, Brooklyn founded in 1889 and still in operation today.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The bulk of this collection was donated by the Montauk Club in April 2016. Additional materials were later donated by Mary Brennan and Dylan Yeats. Lisa Finstrom and Tim Sanford gave materials to the club in 2006 which the club later added to this collection.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in 5 series by type, one of which has subseries. The series and subseries are as follows: Series 1: Administration; Series 2: Publications; Series 3: Membership; Series 4: Photos and Prints; and Series 5: Events with Subseries 1: Menus, Invitations and Programs and Subseries 2: Chauncey Depew Dinners. Folders and items are arranged chronologically within the series and subseries.
Historical note
The Montauk Club was founded in 1889 in Park Slope, an affluent neighborhood in what was then the independent city of Brooklyn. Though there were many other upper-class social clubs in Brooklyn at the time, the Montauk Club quickly became one of the most desirable memberships. Among the 25 charter members was Alfred Chapin, then mayor of Brooklyn, as well as future mayor David Boody and Lieutenant Governor Timothy Woodruff. Charles A. Moore was the club's first president.
Soon after incorporating, the club selected a site for their clubhouse and commissioned the architect Francis H. Kimball to build it. Kimball designed an opulent structure in Venetian Gothic style which still stands today on the corner of 8th Avenue and Lincoln Place. The building was completed in 1891. The Landmarks Commission designated it as an individual landmark in 1966.
The club has hosted many events and famous persons. In 1892, a dinner was held for former President Grover Cleveland. In 1895, an estimated 5,000 people attended a reception for Governor (soon to be President) McKinley. For 35 years starting in 1892, the club hosted annual birthday dinners for Chauncey Depew, an attorney and politician who was very well-known at the time. These celebrations became nearly as famous as the man himself, and were reported on nationally and internationally.
In 1934, during the Great Depression, the club's financial situation became so dire that the board voted to dissolve. Two dissenting votes, and opposition from the membership, reversed the decision and the club survived. Later in the twentieth century, membership and revenue once again declined as social clubs fell out of favor. In the mid-1990s, the club sold its upper floors for development into condominiums, while retaining the first and second floors. The sale allowed the Montauk Club to remain in its original building, and it is still open and functioning in that building today.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Depew, Chauncey M. Speech by Hon. Chauncey M. Depew on his 89th birthday at the Montauk Club, Brooklyn, N.Y., April 28th, 1923. CT275.D473 A5 1923 - as well as various other birthday speeches given at the Club by Depew.
The Montauk Club of Brooklyn. Eagle Press, 1890. 367 B87 M
Rubin, Lucas. Brooklyn's Sportsmen's Row: politics, society & the sporting life on northern Eighth Avenue. The History Press, 2012. GV584.5.N4 R82 2012
Brooklyn ephemera collection (BCMS.0007), folders Clubs: Montauk Club I & II and Menus: Montauk Club.
Brooklyn Historical Society ephemera collection (ARC.272)
Photographs from the Brooklyn Daily Eagle (BCMS.0002), folder Clubs: Social: Montauk Club.
News coverage via Brooklyn Newsstand (bklyn.newspapers.com) and the Local Newspapers on Microfilm Collection (BCMS.0028)
Everett and Evelyn Ortner papers and photographs (ARC.306)
Park Slope Civic Council (PSCC) records (BCMS.0083)
Brooklyn clubs collection (ARC.172)
Scope and Contents
While this collection does not constitute a comprehensive record of the Montauk Club's activities, it chronicles events spanning the club's entire history, including documents pertaining to the club's administration, membership, and events as well as a small number of photographs and bound volumes. The early event materials are particularly noteworthy; many of the event programs and menus are elaborately and lavishly decorated.
Clubs; Menus; Park Slope (New York, N.Y.); Park Slope Historic District (New York, N.Y.)
- Series 1: Administration
  - Original Documents, 1889-1919 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Indenture/mortgage, 1889 (Box 10)
  - Visitors' Book, 1914-1935 (Box 9)
  - Original Documents, 1934-2008 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - General administrative materials, 1928-1960 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Appraisal, 1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Financial Reports, 1937-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Treasurer's Reports, 1936-1945 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Assembly Permits, 1961-1966 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Promotional materials, c.1990s-early 2000s (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Ephemera, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Sheet music for "Montauk Club March", undated (Box 10)
- Series 2: Publications and clippings
  - Brooklyn Eagle articles, 1889-1941 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Book, "The Montauk Club", 1890 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Leslie's Illustrated Newspaper article, 1890 (Box 10)
  - "A Little History of the Montauk Club", c. 1910 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Clippings, 1980s-1990s (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - "The Montauk Club - A Brief History", undated (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - "Members' Guide" and "Montauk Club Interior" handouts, circa 2000s (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Writings on club history by Mary Brennan, 2010s (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - "The Montauk Club, 1889-2016" by Mary Brennan, 2018 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series 3: Membership
  - Bound directories, 1892-2019 (Box 2)
  - New member proposal sheets, 1941-1949 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Membership Application, 2017-2018 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newsletters, 1971-1994 (Box 3, Folder 1-21)
  - Newsletters, 2005-2017 (Box 4, Folder 1-13)
- Series 4: Photos and Prints
  - Building Exterior (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Building Interior (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Building Interior from The American Architect, 1895 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - People and Events (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Oversize Photos (Box 10)
- Series 5: Events
  - Subseries 1: Menus, Invitations and Programs
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1891-1906 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1909-1919 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1920 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1930s-1940s (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1950s (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1960s (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1970s (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1980s (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 1990s (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Menus, Invitations and Programs, 2000s (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Theatre Party Programs, 1895-1900 (Box 6, Folder 3-8)
    - Dinner Party Programs, 1897-1904 (Box 6, Folder 9-16)
    - Dinner Party Programs, 1906-2008 (Box 7, Folder 1-9, 15)
    - Brooklyn Historical Pageant, 1915 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Music Concerts, 1979-1997 (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - New Year's Eve Parties, 1990s-2000s (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - New member welcome events, 2006-2019 (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - Anniversary celebrations, 1989-2014 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Wine cellar, circa 1990s (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Auctions, 1990s (Box 7, Folder 17)
  - Subseries 2: Chauncey Depew Dinners
    - Chauncey Depew Dinners, 1892-1899 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Chauncey Depew Dinners, 1900-1909 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Chauncey Depew Dinners, 1910 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Chauncey Depew Dinners, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Chauncey Depew Dinners, 1913 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Chauncey Depew Dinners, 1990s (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Chauncey Depew Information Packets (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Chauncey Depew speeches, 1911-1912 (Box 8, Folder 8)